

Joao Pinheiro Neto, PhD

💌 joaoxp@gmail.com | 🏕 joaopn.github.io | 🖸 joaopn | 🛅 joaopn | 🎓 Google Scholar | ORCID

Summary.

Physicist with experience in modeling collective dynamics of complex systems. I specialize in data analysis of large datasets, with an emphasis on data quality and sampling effects. Currently working on how the structure of social media impacts opinion spreading in social networks.

Education & Academic Experience _____

University of Graz Graz, Austria

POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER

June 2024 -

- · IDea Lab (PI: Prof. Dr. Jana Lasser)
- · Funding: Austrian Science Fund

RWTH Aachen University Aachen, Germany

POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER • Chair for Computational Social Sciences and Humanities (PI: Prof. Dr. Jana Lasser)

- · Funding: University of Konstanz

University of Konstanz Konstanz, Germany

POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER

Feb. 2023 - Sep. 2023

Nov. 2023 - Jun. 2024

- · Social Data Science Lab, Department of Politics and Public Administration (PI: Prof. Dr. David Garcia)
- · Funding: University of Konstanz

Max Planck Institute for Dynamics and Self-Organization

POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER

Göttingen, Germany Jan. 2021 - Jan. 2023

Göttingen, Germany

Nov. 2013 - Mar. 2014

- · Physics of Social Systems Group, Department of Dynamics of Complex Fluids (PI: Prof. Dr. Stephan Herminghaus
- Funding: Max Planck Society

Georg August University of Göttingen

PhD in Physics Nov. 2017 - Jan. 2021

• Title: Criticality and sampling in neuronal networks (supervisor: Prof. Dr. Viola Priesemann)

• Title: A study on the dynamics of neural networks (supervisor: Prof. Dr. José Antônio Brum)

Funding: Brazilian Council for Scientific and Technological Development & Max Planck Society

State University of Campinas

MSc in Physics

Feb. 2012 - Dec. 2014

• Funding: São Paulo Research Foundation

University of Bremen Bremen, Germany

• Guest at the Complex Systems Lab (supervisor: Prof. Dr. Stefan Bornholdt)

• Funding: São Paulo Research Foundation

State University of Campinas

BSc in Physics Feb. 2008 - Dec. 2011

Coding Skills

GUEST RESEARCHER

Proficient python, SQL, MongoDB, LLM stack, MATLAB, git, bash

Basic R, Julia, Mathematica, C/C++

Professional Experience ____

University of Graz Graz, Austria

POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER

Jun. 2024 -

- Modeling and data analysis of multiple social media platforms.
- · Large-scale data scraping and data cleaning
- Creation and maintenance of terabyte-range databases and data infrastructure
- Research on application of Large Language Models to computational social science

RWTH Aachen University

Aachen, Germany

POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER

- Teaching of graduate-level courses for the CSS masters program.
- Co-supervision of 4 masters students.
- Modeling and data analysis of multiple social media platforms.
- Research on application of Large Language Models to computational social science

University of Konstanz Konstanz Konstanz, Germany

POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER

- Modeling and data analysis of multiple social media platforms.
 Creation and maintenance of multi-billion-object PostgreSQL and MongoDB databases.
- · Writing of grant proposals to research online platforms.
- Teaching of graduate-level university courses.

Max Planck Institute for Dynamics and Self-Organization

Göttingen, Germany Jan. 2021 - Jan. 2023

Nov. 2023 - May 2024

Feb 2023 -

POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER

- Modeling and data analysis of multiple social media platforms.
- · Data scraping and data cleaning.
- Creation and maintenance of multi-billion-object MongoDB databases.
- Network and NLP analysis of social media data.
- Supervision of 3 BSc students.

Max Planck Institute for Dynamics and Self-Organization

Göttingen, Germany

 PHD Candidate
 Feb. 2015 - Jan 2021

- Data analysis of large-scale experimental data in Neuroscience, using methods from Physics, Network Theory and Information Theory.
- Development of fast network dynamics simulations using CUDA and parallelization in MATLAB.
- Signal processing and filtering of timeseries.

Research Publications

- Supervision of 3 MSc students, and tutoring in several university block seminars.
- Modeling of COVID-19 spread using Bayesian inference.

State University of Campinas

Campinas, Brazil

STUDENT Feb. 2008 - Dec. 2014

- Modelling of large-scale dynamical networks using methods from Network Theory (clustering, community detection, etc).
- HPC simulations of particle physics interactions and development of a software to interpolate simulation results.
 Teaching assistant for undergraduate classes. Disciplines: Experimental Physics I (2009, 2011), Probability I (2010)

- 6. **Neto, J. P.**, F. P. Spitzner, and V. Priesemann (2022). Sampling effects and measurement overlap can bias the inference of neuronal avalanches. *PLOS Computational Biology*, 18(11):1–22
- 5. F. P. Spitzner, J. Dehning, J. Wilting, A. Hagemann, **J. P. Neto**, J. Zierenberg, and V. Priesemann (2021). Mr. estimator, a toolbox to determine intrinsic timescales from subsampled spiking activity. *PLOS ONE*, 16:e0249447
- 4. J. Dehning, J. Zierenberg, F. P. Spitzner, M. Wibral, **J. P. Neto**, M. Wilczek, and V. Priesemann (2020). Inferring change points in the spread of covid-19 reveals the effectiveness of interventions. *Science*, 369:eabb9789
- 3. J. Dehning, F. P. Spitzner, M. C. Linden, S. B. Mohr, **J. P. Neto**, J. Zierenberg, M. Wibral, M. Wilczek, and V. Priesemann (2020). Model-based and model-free characterization of epidemic outbreaks. *medRxiv*, page 2020.09.16.20187484
- 2. J. Wilting, J. Dehning, **J. P. Neto**, L. Rudelt, M. Wibral, J. Zierenberg, and V. Priesemann (2018). Operating in a reverberating regime enables rapid tuning of network states to task requirements. *Frontiers in Systems Neuroscience*, 12
- 1. **J. P. Neto**, de M. A. M. Aguiar, J. A. Brum, and S. Bornholdt (2017). Inhibition as a determinant of activity and criticality in dynamical networks. *arXiv*: 1712.08816